[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se - radio dotnet.
se radio brings you relevant and detailed discussions of software engineering topics at least once a month.
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E software magazine online at computer or / software.
this is Robert Berman for software engineering radio.
I'm joined by grant Ingersoll.
grant is the chief scientist at lucid imagination.
a committer on the Apache Solr and Lucene projects.
the author of the books taming texts.
and the founder of the Apache mahout project which we will be discussing today.
grant welcome back to software engineering radio.
thank you glad to be here.
yeah I say welcome back because grant was our guest on a previous episode 187.
about search and the solar search engine.
today grant you and I will be discussing Apache mahout and machine learning.
first can you tell us what is machine learning? sure yeah.
I know it's it's a great question because I think a lot of people when they hear.
I think hear the phrase machine learning.
they often think about you know computers taking over the world and things like that.
but they're really what machine learning is trying to do.
is look at previous examples or essentially a historical view of of your data.
and then try to make predictions about what that data is doing.
typically using some sort of statistical analysis of that data.
so the common common things to think about what machine learning is.
if you have say you're taking in all of the world's news.
and you want to be able to classify it into buckets.
that says you know this article is about sports or this article is about politics.
that's a classic example of machine learning or at Kent.
that's kind of problem that can be solved with machine learning.
you're often looking ways to organize your data into into something.
that is more easily consumable by people.
grant what are some other problem cases that machine learning addresses successfully?
sure yeah this is a pretty wide variety it sure as it turns out.
so that the general scope a classification there's a number of use cases.
it's commonly used in in fraud analytics.
detecting whether for instance somebody is committing credit-card fraud.
it's used in analysis of healthcare records.
except to try to identify patients who are at risk.
so if for instance you've ever had a EKG or if you've gone for some expensive tests.
there may be very well be machine learning being applied there to help doctors narrow down.
you've also probably seen machine learning.
if you've ever done for instance online dating or something like that.
or if you've gone to Amazon and you've bought something.
and then it's recommending other products to you.
so anytime you you have this kind of question of people who bought this also bought that.
that's a classic machine learning example.
I've seen it used pretty successfully in utility companies for instance.
where they take all of their input from their smart grid.
you know that is part of the the power supply.
and essentially they use tools like clustering to try to detect anomalies in the system.
so if you know if set of machines or capabilities on the smart grid.
they produce kind of what you would call a normal signal right.
by by the fact that they're operating correctly and and so all of those signals will cluster together.
and then any outlier it may very well be representative of something that is wrong in that system.
so there's a wide variety of use cases.
also you know anybody is familiar with like what IBM Watson did on the Jeopardy program.
a whole lot of machine learning it goes into that in terms of taking the text.
taking the questions taking the answers that they have.
and parsing that language trying to figure out what exactly the answer or the question is.
and then providing back a suitable response.
so all of those are I think pretty good examples of using machine learning.
to solve highly complex problems.
maybe I'm taking the expression machine learning to literally.
but does it mean that the machine learns or is it us who learned from the machine?
machine is just doing what you tell it to do right.
so what what is learning in this sense.
is that it's looking at past examples.
then using that to try to figure out how to predict some future event or some current event right. so if you know 10 times out of 10.
when when a certain article comes in and mentions I don't know Alex Rodriguez.
in the New York Yankees some human has said this article is about baseball.
the machine can learn that pattern.
and obviously what you're typically talking about is much more complex problems.
where there's a lot of different variables that come into play.
we as humans aren't so great at being able to deal with a lot of variables that wants us.
but but the computer can often do that by looking at a lot of examples.
and trying to figure out what the probabilities are of things occurring the way they occur.
and then and then make guesses based on those probabilities going forward.
so it's not you know I guess it also depends on what your definition of learning is -. oh sure.
can you talk about the distinction between supervised and unsupervised machine learning?
sure so the supervised does it kind of the name implies.
is there there's some there's some human in the loop if you will.
in the sense that what you typically do is you take some amount of data.
that you've collected over time and you split it up into usually two groups.
but it may be more than two groups.
and then for the you pick one group out of that.
and you have people actually go through and apply labels or to that content.
so for instance in the using the news example again.
you maybe would have you know a hundred articles or a thousand articles.
and you would have some people we go through and actually apply labels.
based on their their judge right.
so now you have the answer to those 1000 articles right.
and then you would take and feed that into the training part of the algorithm.
and it would essentially learn what words are associated with which topics. and it would output a model.
you then would take that model and hook it into your main program.
such that anytime any new article comes in.
you would simply be asking the model what label should I apply to this.
on supervised as the the name also applies of course is.
there's there's no human involved.
so what we're trying to do is use pure statistical techniques or algorithmic approaches.
to try to figure out how to group or organize content.
so in many cases clustering is often an example of unsupervised learning.
because you're just simply looking at what are what what is similar.
between these two documents or these two items.
whereas you know the classification or the news article stuff.
is often done as a supervised task.
because you have some you know you have some human who's doing the annotations or the labels.
ahead of time.
okay is machine learning the same as data mining or is that's something different?
formal definition wise I think they're pretty similar.
data mining probably is inclusive of machine learning.
they're all trying to get at what are the patterns and formulas or whatever.
that describe those data in appropriate ways.
with you know all with the goal of surfacing relevant information up and out to users.
such that they can make better decisions on it.
you know I don't know specific the formal definitions.
somebody else probably could jump in on those.
okay so and of course they've changed over the years as well.
but I would say data mine could also include rule-based systems.
or other kinds of systems and aren't necessarily a learning approach.
okay would it be fair to say that machine learning is becoming an increasingly significant part. of modern applications?
yeah I think that's probably an understatement.
especially when you talk about on the web or any place that you're dealing with large volumes of data.
ie a big data movement a lot of I think what's powering that is the need is machine learning.
so if you go to the googles and the Facebook's.
or basically anytime you're on on the web these days.
chances are there's somebody who's using machine learning techniques.
to try to get a better understanding of what you're doing.
ad targeting or advertising on the web is a classic another classic example of machine learning.
you know where they're simply asking the question should I show this ad to this person or not.
so based on their profile they're asking the question of their models what.
whether this is a relevant ad or not.
and chances are they're doing that using machine learning approaches.
is this growth then is it primarily because we have a lot more data.
or because we have enough capacity to process the data now.
or because these algorithms have been discovered and tuned or all of the above?
yeah I think it's all of the above.
I mean I think you know as I mentioned earlier.
we these humans aren't necessarily capable of processing that much data.
and so you need and at the same time computers are really good at doing.
you know these kind of statistical pattern recognition kind of things.
and so the combination of the two things is I think what helps keep us afloat.
and in many regards and it's also you know.
as Google and Facebook and the like have proven.
it's often a differentiator in terms of business capabilities as well.
because if you can have a better understanding of what your users are doing with your content.
then you can better target and/or refine.
I learn from what they're doing to make it better in the future.
which presumably attracts more used users etc.
our business is then usually able to quantify the impact.
or the return on investment of implementing machine learning.
or implementing a particular machine learning feature?
yeah I think in many cases they are.
the you know that's been using machine learning techniques for a quite a number of years.
and I think generally speaking they do pretty well.
their spam finding and identifying spam there's another classic machine learning approach.
our technique a classification problem.
I think most spam detectors these days do a pretty good job at least in my view.
when I look at my Inbox anyways I have that sense granted.
that you know in those kinds of situations where you have an adversary.
there always seems to be a back-and-forth as as each side adjusts their algorithms.
so this this stuff typically is not you know do it once deploy it.
and you're done kind of situation.
you have to reevaluate your models on a periodic basis.
and make sure you're capturing feedback from from your users and your system.
such a good feed feed that back in.
that point you've just raised about feedback.
that's something I find very interesting.
and I'm gonna ask you some more about that.
when we get into the particulars of recommendations and clustering.
another general machine learning question I have is.
what kind of sizes of data sets are we talking about here.
and how long does it take to run sure machine learning algorithm.
are we talking millions hundred millions?
it depends on the situation and the amount of data you have.
I mean some of them some algorithms are the sequential.
and will only run on you know for instance one machine.
so what's often happens there as you take.
if you have a lot of data you're going to down sample or take a sample of that data.
and then apply your techniques to it.
and it tends to be a little bit more hand tuning around it.
but certainly you know when you're talking internet scale.
you can have millions and millions or hundreds of millions or billions of events.
and and they're you know obviously there's no you need a parallel or distributed approach.
that's going to help you do this is so what you know.
what you've seen in the past few years around the big data movement.
of course there's more and more algorithms that are designed.
to take advantage of distributed computation models right.
and so you know for instance I was just in Japan a few weeks ago.
and I was talking to one large online mobile social gaming sites there.
and you know they have four hundred million users.
and they're doing you know I don't know how many games they have.
but if you start to think about the size of that matrix.
400 million users times however many things they're tracking it.
that's a quite a large matrix and so you need distributed techniques to be able to deal with that.
can you tell us anything about what this platform was doing with machine learning?
I saw there's a variety of things you know one was being able to understand and recommend games.
so if you know if you bought a particular game.
than being able to recommend other games.
all the users who are similar to you may have bought or used.
that's probably a pretty classic online example you know.
but they also some of these systems also can factor in the way players play in the game.
to then tune you know what happens in the game based on these kind of statistical patterns right.
so if you were doing really well.
and if some of this is artificial intelligence obviously as well.
but being able to you know detectable how fast you're going through a game.
then you can make it easier or harder I think those are options as well.
are these algorithms typically then run on a large batch of data.
or once it's been trained can you then take classification as an example.
classify each new event as it hits the system within a interactive type of latency.
so for instance has some I'm sure but has some algorithms.
that are what we call online learners.
they can be updated interactively and others are more batch oriented.
so it really depends on the type of algorithm.
so you know and then you you want to make appropriate choices around your needs.
often it's the case that the online or the batch ones.
you can you can obviously deal with a lot more data.
because you can distribute that work.
and you know it may take you an hour two or even longer to build the model.
but once you have them very rich model.
where at the online ones you know you're you're making some trade-offs there.
about how much data you can look at in order to be able to make decisions much more rapidly.
and update the decision incrementally as you go right.
if I buy a book at online bookseller about a subject I've never bought books before.
they might be able to update my recommendations of books I might like immediately.
based on now they've discovered that I'm interested in this new topic.
yeah I don't know you know I'm not familiar with some of the inner workings of those companies at that level.
as to what they do I'm sure they have a combination of machine learning plus rule-based systems.
but but yeah I mean you want to be able to instantly look at what happened.
you know what books you bought compare that with books that other users have bought.
and then be able to essentially kind of put you in a neighborhood.
or put you around people who are who are like you that way.
and then make recommendations based on things that you have not bought.
and that they think you might be able like.
and usually you can update that pretty quickly.
or but oftentimes it's maybe you know within a day or so right.
because it's not it's not always that urgent.
and it's it oftentimes if you've been a customer there long enough.
it's not necessarily going to change drastically in a very shorter.
or they know that I shop on that site once a week.
so if they don't get me this time they'll get me next time. that's exactly right.
okay grant now I'd like to shift gears into the mout project. what is the Mahajan?
sure so how it is an Apache Software Foundation project.
just like we mentioned earlier with lucina's solar.
that's there was a simple goal of building.
I just mean that simple goal but with the goal of building a scalable machine learning algorithms.
or a scalable machine learning library.
so what we've done is you know what we've done is got together a bunch of people.
who have been working on machine learning in this space.
and try to build out a set of commonly used proven algorithms.
and make sure that they can scale.
in many cases this means we try to use tools like Hadoop and MapReduce type applications.
but in other cases that for some algorithms that aren't easily made parallel.
we just simply try to make sure we have very efficient implementations of those algorithms.
and then you know we want to build community around that.
so there's a large number of practitioners who are who are using and contributing to the project.
and you know of course we want this to be apache licensed.
and so it's free and open source and all of those good things.
is there a story behind how you founded the project?
yeah I guess well it kind of came out of Lucene in the sense.
that I had emailed on the Lucene list I don't even remember when.
this was a few years back that you know kind of looking at how search is evolving.
and how machine learning is often used in helping solve search problem.
or search related problems or text related problems.
and basically saying you know I could see the Lucene project involving.
to have those kinds of things in it.
to fast forward maybe a year and this woman Isabel Droste from Germany.
emails me out of the blue and says hey are you still interested.
in machine learning project at Apache.
and she was also a Lusine user and so we started emailing on it.
and we each reached out to a few other people.
who we knew were interested in in machine learning at the time.
and then we got together and started trying to figure out.
how we could create a machine learning project.
that differentiated itself from some of the other open-source machine learning libraries out there.
and how does what we came up with we had generally thought we would.
this is around with MapReduce and Hadoop we were just starting to take off.
we had originally thought we would solely focus on implementing on Hadoop.
but that has evolved over time too.
so to the point where we're much more pragmatic.
about wanting to just make sure we're delivering scalable machine learning libraries.
using Hadoop where appropriate but using other techniques as well.
because those happen to solve the problem better or in a different way then.
is it accurate to say that Mahad is a toolbox of machine learning algorithms.
that can be mixed and matched according to the problem at hand?
yeah that's exactly and I would say you know.
we tend to focus my how norm people some people call them a hoot some say how.
I tend the same how out of habit I tend to say how.
it focuses on what do we call the three C's.
classification clustering and collaborative filtering.
but we also have you know some utilities and things that help support those.
as well as we have a good number of math libraries.
and tools for efficiently with large collections of you know doubles and floats and stuff like that.
so kind of the under all the underpinnings of these machine learning algorithms are either.
you know matrix algebra linear algebra or a statistical analysis.
and so you need a good set of libraries around those.
but you know primarily focused around those three C's if you will.
well we can reckon I'm sorry what we try to do is pick algorithms that we think are proven out.
and have and are able to scale as opposed to necessarily implementing all the.
you know every X latest and greatest bleeding edge algorithm.
that maybe hasn't been proven out in industry.
yeah grant you talked about scalable algorithms.
can you typically target the same algorithm to Hadoop or single node.
based on the size of the data set.
or are there Hadoop algorithms in single node algorithms that are different algorithms?
some of them are different some are the same.
most of our Hadoop yeah I mean dupe you you can run Hadoop on one node and it'll work just fine.
it will take longer than you know the same algorithm coded up to run on just one known.
but obviously the benefit is that you can scale it out.
you can just simply add nodes and Hadoop should be able to scale with that.
so most of our Hadoop implementations also have a sequential version.
that we often code up as a reference implementation.
but they're also perfectly usable.
and then other algorithms simply have no Hadoop equivalent.
and those you know those typically just run on a single machine.
but they often you know we try to make them as fast as possible.
or you can distribute them in other ways.
so for instance the classic example for that I'm how is what's called stochastic gradient descent.
Oh kind of a mouthful but it's a form of logistic regression.
ie you're trying to essentially draw a line between objects.
that you're you're measuring.
that one's completely sequential in maja but it's also very fast.
and it's also something you can wear you can deploy the models in a kind of replicated environment.
so you can serve up a very large number of classification results all at once.
just by your can creating a multi-threaded approach or a replicated.
what are some of the flagship users of how project that you're aware of?
and what are they doing with it?
yeah well you know open-source is you don't always know who is using.
I I continuously meet people who are doing interesting things.
of the ones that are public I know they declare they're doing with it.
but they don't always declare you know what exactly they bill.
say we're using it but they don't always say in what way.
I know for instance Twitter uses it.
I'm not sure what parts of it they're using.
I know Foursquare uses the recommendations library.
I know I'm pretty sure Amazon's IMDB are some part of their movie recommendations. is powered by my house.
many people are using the recommendation capability that's been.
it's been around the longest probably has the most number of features.
and is what often attracts people to how.
that being said you know I I know some advertising companies for instance.
who are using Mahara at very large scales to do classification.
to basically answer that question should I show this add to this ayudar or not.
I met I've met a number of people in government who are who are using it.
to be able to classify and organize content.
in fact I met somebody the other day who was using it for doing classification.
on a tunnel maintenance vehicle or something like the heavens.
so it really is it a quite a wide variety of cases.
I know personally at loose it works we we use it a number of ways in our Big Data product.
we provide clustering on the Box we provide classification as a service.
we also do things like try to both identify what we call statistically interesting phrases.
we also do use it to detect duplicate documents.
so you know there's there's quite a large variety of usages.
you mentioned a few minutes ago you are trying to create a project.
that was differentiated from the competitive or from the competition.
how is mahou differentiated from some other machine learning packages out there? yeah that's a great question.
I mean of course some of this has changed over time as the Big Data movement is has come on.
but you know one I think there's a few things one.
many open-source machine learning algorithms at the time.
were either very research oriented oriented or they you know they.
we didn't particularly care for the open source license that they have.
because maybe our work restricted us from using that particular license.
so you know the apache license is very permissive in terms of usages.
and so you know being up at people who had already worked at apache. that was very comfortable to us.
many of them at the time did not have good documentation around it.
and then also many of them did not scale.
and so that doesn't mean there's you know not scaling isn't necessarily.
it doesn't mean it's not useful but in our particular case. you know the people who founded this and worked on the project.
we really wanted to make sure these algorithms are scalable.
this you know since then this was you know four or five years ago I guess.
it's been already you know the space has evolved quite a bit.
and I think you know any of those cases still stand for us.
but it also is is a Balmain as well.
you talked about the origin of the project as in your mind at the time.
a extended feature set on Lucene and solar.
could you say more about what is the relationship between machine learning and search?
that's a great question. I mean this to categorize it as as a extension of those.
although there's there certainly are places you can use machine learning and search.
you know a common use case that I have is as contents coming in.
I want to I want to classify that content I want to put labels on it right.
and then I'll feed that into you know as those documents get indexed into my search engine.
I will then you know obviously index those those new labels too.
and so then in my search user interface as user search I may show up.
I may show facets that that show what those labels are.
because essentially what you're helping the user do is.
get a better sense of what this content is about right.
and so you know if you can show up labels that say you know here's a hundred results.
50 of them are about Sports 30 or about politics 10 or about whatever and on and on.
until I filled it out that can essentially help the users browser.
navigate to the content that they may be more interested in.
there's also a number of other ways and in search oftentimes.
being able to bring in some of these social network into the relevancy of the results.
so the tools like recommendations can often be used there.
or recommendation tools there's even movement.
and it's primarily academic this point which is called learning to rank.
which is actually trying to figure out.
what the search symbol or similarity scores are based based on classification.
you also often see machine learning and when you want to try to personalize the search results.
so you know for instance if you log in to Google or Bing or any of those.
try to use your past history your user profile all of that.
they feed that into machine learning techniques to build models.
about what results you would be interested in.
then they use that at run time when you do searches to tailor results to you.
I say yeah quite a quite a bit of applications.
and then of course at the I love actually parsing and looking at the language.
being able to do things like identify the parts of speech in the content.
being able to identify phrases being able to identify more semantic relationships in the content.
those are often also solved using machine learning approaches, that is very interesting I.
what I'm thinking is if I was a clothing retailer.
I know that every SKU this is a shirt this is pants these are shoes.
and I could I don't need somebody else I don't need a tool to classify my garments.
into what type of garment they are.
but if you're pulling in documents articles things that come off the internet.
this approach fills in that information that you have already have about a physical project.
a physical product with machine classifications or machine learning attributes.
that help improve the search results.
yeah and actually even on your ear the product example.
I mean imagine if you will that you're an aggregator of products from a lot of different manufacturers.
oftentimes that that data is noisy or it's incomplete etc.
machine learning can kind of help fill in the gaps you know but making a mistake.
this stuff isn't perfect either this is something that evolves over time.
you know one of the the principles of this is that you you have to feed back into the system.
to help correct it when it's wrong you know.
and in many cases you can be on par with what humans are able to do.
in other cases you know if humans may simply be better at it.
but of course they don't scale as well in terms of dealing large large amounts of content right.
and so it's always kind of this back-and-forth.
the most successful systems I've seen there is.
there still is some human-in-the-loop if you will.
that is helping guide the system or giving feedback as to how to improve the results. but you know as you get more and more data.
you can often take advantage of those kind of implicit suggestions.
by the fact that users click on something or they don't click on something.
and then you can use that as feedback to the question.
of how the inline user improves the results.
I think that's very important.
I'm going to come back to that when we talk about some specific machine learning algorithms.
I want to wrap up a little bit on them a how project overview. what language is it written in?
I would love to try a large majority was Java.
I'm trying to think if we have anything else in there.
I'm in Hadoop this Java based I think so.
we're primarily a Java project.
I know some people have contributed Apache pig scripts.
and so if you qualify that as an actual programming language.
then maybe you can say that there might be some Python.
or other things sprinkled the inner bash scripts sprinkled in.
as as utilities around using the out.
but the large majority of the code and the algorithms are our Java based.
how many how the project structured in terms of people or any people?
yeah how many committers are there how many is there a community around it how active is it?
yeah I think there's a pretty large community there.
number of committers as I would say roughly 15.
you know it's an open source project it's at Apache most people are volunteers.
so you know things come and go in terms of people contributing.
and what they wanted what their interest level is etc.
which is kind of the open source way.
we are working towards our 1.0 release we just had what we call point eight.
so right now we're primarily focused on you know cleaning up the API.
is cleaning up the documentation.
making sure that this is something you know once we hit 1.0.
that these are the api's we want to support in the backwards compatible.
we do take in some new algorithms now.
but we're primarily focused on the ones that we have already and making sure that they work well.
and so that's you know that's the primary focus.
great well that kind of wraps up the general how questions I have for you.
I want to talk now a little bit about each of the three C's you mentioned.
recommendation clustering and classification.
I guess that recommendation is a C if you call it collaborative filtering. yeah.
let's start with recommendation we've been talking about it but let's reset with this question.
what is recommendation?
so the goal here is that your collaborative filtering.
so there's I guess you could say there's typically two kinds of recommendations.
one being which is not in being content-based recommendations.
which is taking information about the user.
and/or the items that you want to recommend.
and try to try to understand it as some deeper level.
what is intrinsic about those things that you could recommend them to the user.
collaborative filtering on the other hand.
is simply just using the votes of users and/or actors in the system.
to then you know group all of that together.
and make try to understand which neighborhood some new user fits in.
and then make recommendations based that way.
so it's collaborative filtering is more of just simply a voting mechanism.
so you know if everybody is buying some particular booking.
and you're similar term you're similar to those people.
then we should recommend that book to you based on the fact.
that there's a large number of votes for that item right. even though you know where it's content-based.
one would try to say oh well this person likes to read computer books.
and this is a computer book and so on and so forth that the tuition behind it is.
grant we're gonna try to find users like you.
then we're going to recommend to you some of the more popular items.
that users like you like that you have not seen or bought or read yet.
yeah and so that's that's one one of two approaches under cloud roof filtering.
that typically would be called user based similarity. or user based recommendations.
which is we're gonna find users like you.
and then we're gonna find what items they've bought or looked at or whatever.
and then make recommendations off those.
the the other approach is called item based similarity.
and typically it's just kind of flipping the question around a little bit.
it's like it's taking items you've bought.
and then trying to figure out what items are similar to those items.
based on what other people have bought.
so it's it's a slightly different I guess when it comes to the math.
but it hopefully returns similar results or better results in some cases.
so and then there are a few other approaches around collaborative filtering too.
but those are the two main ones.
when you're talking about this step where we try to find the users that are like you.
what what is the concept of likeness that one of these algorithms would use?
you know it's a good question. I mean it's sort of a habit in particular.
this is a pluggable concept generally called generally we use this notion of similarity or a distance.
because in many situations with these algorithms what you're looking at.
and this actually goes back to our search interview.
you're looking at some n dimensional vector space.
and you're you're essentially asking what is what is the distance between these two vector.
and so you you know there's a number of different ways to calculate distance.
and so and my how that will be that's all pluggable.
and you can you know we should with a number different distance measures.
but you can also plug in your own.
so you could use for instance the classic Euclidean distance.
I you know how how the crow flies if you will.
you can use the met see the taxicab distance.
you can also use things like cosine similarity and a bunch of other ones.
so that's it's a very pluggable notion.
and what people typically do is test based on their data.
and the properties of their data they'll choose an appropriate distance.
and then you know test them to see that it produces reasonable results.
the vector then is the set of items that you have already read or bought or.
done something with?
yeah typically it's not the data about yourself.
like your age and your address and your things like attributes that they might know about you.
it's usually just accounts for instance of you know all the all the votes.
for a particular item or night.
and then you're essentially you get this large matrix out of it.
that you're doing these these distance calculations.
where you're comparing your this your particular users purchase habits or whatever.
with that larger matrix to see which ones overlap.
you said there the similarity function is pluggable.
and I would guess there are going to be other ways to tune these algorithms.
if I have a bunch of data I've run some recommendations on it.
how do I know when I'm done or how do I evaluate the quality of the results.
that the algorithm produced?
yeah that's a great question.
because you know one you're never done.
but at the same time you have to we all have to ship our code and put it into production.
so we we do provide it how for instance some tools.
for trying to evaluate the quality of your data.
what often is done in this situation is.
you have some amount of data already that's obviously feeding in the system.
and so you have passed answers that you've given.
and so what you can do is with some of that data out of out of the training of the system.
and then just simply run that data through and see what results you get.
so it's kind of a hold hold out some amount and then process.
many people will have user groups or you know focus groups that they'll ask people.
that the system or they have you know their own Quality Assurance team or relevance team in the house.
other people will do a be testing where they put this data up online.
and you know that some percentage of users get the the new recommendations.
and some percent don't get any recommendations or get the old recommendations.
and so then you could look at whatever metrics you track as an organization.
to see whether you're doing better or not.
the you know in in me at least an e-commerce it's often.
you know are people buying more things or not.
are they are they actually clicking on the recommendations.
and then buying those items or not.
so there's really a variety of ways you can try to figure out.
whether you're being effective or not.
if I'm writing a conventional program generally there's a clear idea of what it's supposed to do.
and I can write a test case say it does what it's supposed to do.
well I think you're saying here is in a recommendation.
especially an e-commerce setting.
that the definition of a good result is really market driven.
and that depends on user behaviors when presented with the new recommendations.
which inherently isn't is not possible to totally predict.
because if you could totally predict the user behavior.
you would do that instead of using my house.
you're dealing with these kind of fuzzy problems you know.
you have a couple different levels of testing.
obviously you've got to make sure that the system you know functions and works.
just like any other program.
but so so just like any you know like in programming obviously.
have your your functional testing and all that to make sure everything's working at a system level.
but then in these kind of problems where there's this notion of where it's a bit fuzzy.
or where there's a subjective experience.
you know there there really isn't necessarily a perfect way.
to to get at the whether this is working and exactly right or not.
and and like you said if you if you knew if you knew the answer ahead of time.
well then you would just do that.
and so what you typically see our approaches where.
you know again you're doing like the a/b testing.
or you're you're doing you're tracking what some user groups do or early beta testers etc.
and so when you can but you can of course capture all of that information.
and then feed that back into your internal testing.
but you know keeping in mind that as you improve the system over time.
those results may change.
and so that you may need to go and update your tests again in the future.
so yeah it requires some some bit of higher-level thinking around testing.
but you know you can you can typically you typically know it when you see it.
and it's it you can tell when the system's being effective that way.
and then they in particularly there's often ways you can measure it via things like.
you know what are people are purchasing more or they're.
you know they're reporting that they have better results and so on.
it sounds like a great opportunity to roll out a couple different algorithms.
to small slices of your user base and evaluate how they perform in the real world.
before you roll it out to your entire user base?
yeah I know that's exactly it.
that's this you know this notion of a be testing.
you know which I think you're starting to see more and more movement in this space is that.
you're always experimenting there is no one answer.
that you ever definitively say is you know the final answer.
and we're just going to leave that deployed for you know the next six months.
or until the next major product release.
I think people who design these kinds of systems.
you know one of the best pieces of advice around it is.
just simply you have to build the experimentation into it from day one.
this cannot be something you go and think about doing after it's up and running.
because you know by definition you're you're dealing with subjective answers.
and so if you're not delivering quality results to your users.
then your system is going to fail no matter how well the scales are.
no matter how well it's engineered sure.
okay well we've been talking about collaborative filtering.
and some of these discussions I'm sure are relevant to other algorithms.
let's move on and talk a little bit about clustering what is clustering grant?
sure so clustering is a non supervisor typically a non supervised learning task.
word where you're trying to automatically group together similar items.
you know so finding users who are alike or who documents are alike.
people who are perhaps Google newsreaders.
they they can see clustering in their everyday lives.
and that on when you go to the Google News page.
there will often be some lead article that they have.
and then there's usually a link just underneath that article.
that says see all you know 5,000 other results like this one.
and so what Google is doing underneath the hood there is an example of time-based clustering.
they're taking all of the content they cluster it into these groups.
and then they're identifying some particular article out of that cluster.
that they think is representative of that content.
presenting it out to you as the user.
and the nice thing about that for us users is.
you know we don't have the time to read all 5,000 of those results.
and so we can just focus in on that one.
and then go read the next representative article about some other thing.
I just say that's a good example of clustering.
and that people may be familiar with just in their day to day lives.
now grant if I had five predetermined groups.
and I said I want two algorithm to sort all these incoming news articles into these five groups.
that is not clustering correct?
now that's typically a classification problem.
if you know those groups ahead of time and you have labels for them.
that's that's typically a classification deputy.
said I mean you can you could treat you you could treat new content coming in.
and you could essentially ask the question which cluster is it close to that close to.
and it's what people often do in the is clustering systems.
where they have new content coming in all the time.
they run their strain algorithm they produce their original sets of clusters.
and then they you know say they may not run it again for let's say another day right.
but the news is of course still coming in.
and so all of that new content that comes in in the meantime.
they may just say okay which cluster is this closest to add to that group.
and so you they're not changing the clusters in that in that time period.
but then the next time you run the clusters may be different.
because those new content new content reshaped the similarity metrics of the system.
that sounds like a great strategy for combining clustering and classification.
to solve real world problems yeah?
how we have classification algorithms that simply sit on top of our clustering algorithms and write. so you're essentially saying.
I know these clusters are the buckets that drifted in let's use them for classification.
you're essentially adding content into them.
and you know underneath the hood the math for solving these kinds of these two problems.
and actually all three of these problems is fairly similar.
so it all starts to look the same algorithmically after a while.
even though they may be approaching in different ways from from the kind of problems.
you're trying to solve sure.
but what I was getting at a couple questions back.
is the clustering you're the algorithm is looking for inherent affinity groupings.
within the data yes not predetermined correct?
right you don't have you don't have any idea upfront of what the groups are typically in clustering.
you say I know I want say ten clusters.
but you have no idea what the labels are for any of those clusters.
now you may try to determine that after you've done the clustering.
but you typically don't know what those labels are up front.
are any of the clustering algorithms good at after you've clustered everything.
saying oh this cluster is Apple News and this cluster is weather or news and so on.
so are they good at identifying what the labels are?
yeah what is the meaning or description of this cluster in a way that's useful to humans.
I mean typically people that's kind of a post processing algorithm.
you know like how we have tools that will go through the clusters.
and find the most common words or phrases in those clusters.
if you're doing texts based off what people often what clustering often produces.
is some notion of a centroid you know what's the center of the cluster.
and so sometimes what people will do is pick whichever document or item.
is closest to the center as the representative item of the of that group.
or they'll go and sample some set of items in that cluster.
and and then use those to show to the user.
but typically you know actually identifying the labels is a post processing technique.
because the you know once you have the cluster it's alright go through.
and figure out what are the key features of that cluster.
grant could you choose a popular clustering algorithm.
and describe at least intuition behind how it works?
I put me on the spot here.
so probably the the one most people start off with in clustering.
and its content of the the the the good one to get started with.
it definitely has some shortcomings but is K means.
that the K and K means means the number of clusters you want.
and so upfront the user picks the K you know it says I want ten clusters.
and then what the algorithm does is chunk through all of the data and it's well.
so so first of it it starts with some sample.
it tries to pick ten ten set example centroids.
or ten example centers of clusters.
and it may either do that randomly or you may seed it.
with what you think they're good centroids to begin with.
it then goes and runs through all of the data.
and calculates the distance of every point to the center's.
and then to that list of centroid so ie the ten centers.
and it then puts that item into into the cluster.
that it's close of the centroid it's closest to that makes sense right.
and it's an iterative algorithm.
so after it's done with that it will then go and update the centroids.
because perhaps it's moved based on the fact that you have this new content.
these new items in the cluster.
and then it essentially repeats and it keeps doing that.
until the center or the centroid has not changed in a significant way.
since the previous run.
so this is an iterative algorithm and in fact it it isn't necessarily guaranteed to converge.
and so what you typically do is you limit the number of iterations it can do.
or you give a convergence threshold that says.
you know if the centroids haven't changed by a certain amount then then stop.
so it's clustering it we've been talking about clustering articles.
is clustering typically something you do to text or can you cluster anything?
if you have a distance metric you can you can cluster most anything.
like I think I mentioned earlier the power or exam or the manufacturing example.
people often do clustering by looking at overtime.
how a particular machine or item is operating.
and then you're trying to instead of it's interested in there.
it's almost the reverse is your clustering everything that's operating normal.
tends to cluster together and then.
so then you're you're less interested in the actual cluster.
but you're more interested in the outliers right.
the things that don't belong to any cluster or at the very fringe of a cluster right.
because those typically represents some event that you're interested in.
and so you know you can also cluster people.
I mean clustering is another way of doing recommendations.
you know put together all the people who have bought similar things.
and then see what you know which items one person bought that the other didn't.
so you can do that off of clustering as well.
clustering texts how do you evaluate a distance metric between two text documents?
so it's actually similar to search here.
I mean what most people do is is a vector space distance manager using like cosine similarity.
so if you have two documents may each create a vector and an n-dimensional space.
if you bring that the tails of those two vectors together that creates an angle.
if you take the cosine of that angle that's usually a pretty good idea of similarity.
because the cosine of the angle 0 is 1.
and you know and then it's goes between minus 1 and 1.
so if they're totally pointing in opposite direction that would be a minus 1.
and then everything in between right.
we were talking about recommendations ultimately.
the test if you're an e-commerce setting is market based.
how do you evaluate when you have when you're clustering algorithm has done a good job.
or two different versions of clustering which one is doing a better job?
yeah that's actually a tough question.
and this is an area definitely of ongoing research.
and it's also an area where I personally have never felt satisfied.
by the ability to do it you know it's to some extent.
so you know when you see it you know when the clusters look righteous.
based on your own intuition of looking at them.
so that's kind of the the smell test if you will.
does the smell right does it look right.
there's also some metrics that people have created over time.
that do things like look at what is the what are the distances of items within the cluster.
and then what are the distances between the centroids of clusters clusters.
and those can be useful metrics as well.
so you know ideally speaking you want your your clusters to be tightly tight together.
very close together and then the the distance between clusters is significant enough.
that you know we as users can delineate between between the clusters easily.
but you know in practice that's often not the case so those become much harder.
most I look at clustering is a way to help users browse.
and/or navigate through content.
and not so much as a way to produce some final answer.
let's move on to classification the third of the three C's what is classification?
so classification is essentially you're trying to answer some question.
like should I show this user this item or not.
or is this a piece of email spam or not.
typically if you're doing binary classification it's an either/or question.
or you could also do multi-label classification.
where you have some set of labels.
and you're trying to pick the one that best represents that piece of content.
according to your training model.
and so it's a supervised learning task.
I have some people who do some upfront work.
trained to produce training data and then you learn a model from that training day.
and then you test that model and then put it into production.
once you're satisfied with the results.
unlike the other two sounds to me like.
it's going to be easier to evaluate a classifier than clustering a recommendation.
because you know the answer.
ah yeah you typically know the answer so it is easier to evaluate.
you you typically have some you know say you have a hundred items see you.
and maybe use 90 of those items as training data.
and then you would keep out ten of them to use this test data.
and now of course I'm you know the hundred is just an example.
you typically have a lot more than that.
but you know it well it tends to be more accurate that way.
you still of course have you know you take two people put them in a room.
and ask them to apply labels and they necessarily agree either.
so you still you still have room for error here.
and or room for people to say no it should be this instead of that.
there would also be the question of whether false positives.
or false negatives are considered more costly for whatever purpose you plan to use it for.
definitely the case.
so you know there's obviously pretty high penalties for being wrong.
so you tend to want a system that's more cautious.
whereas you know if you show somebody the wrong at every now then.
you know that's not necessarily a big deal right.
and so you definitely usually have some sort of cost function associated with what you're doing.
and you also need to take that into account as you build out the system.
what kind of size of data set do you need to train to do a decent job training a classifier?
yeah that's one of the good questions you know it depends on the algorithm.
but usually you're talking at least hundreds or thousands of items per label.
and so you want to make sure you have and of course you need both positive and negative examples.
of that one and so you know you're typically talking thousands.
but or hundreds or thousands you know and really large-scale systems.
you have millions and millions of them just because every time a user clicks or doesn't click.
no that's an answer as to whether this is you know whether you classify correctly or not right.
so in many systems especially large user facing systems.
you have a lot more negative data than you have positive data.
and so with some algorithms you also need to make sure you balance that out.
and so that it can make appropriate decision how to wait for anything.
can you take us under the hood for a classification algorithm?
sure so kind of everybody's favorite classification is called naive Bayes.
and essentially what night Bayes is doing underneath the hood is looking at.
so if you're doing this across tact it's text.
it's essentially looking at what are all the how many times do particular words occur.
with a specific label and it keeps track of that across all of the examples that's a bit seen.
and then uses those as weights in in the model.
such that when some new content comes in.
you're looking at those weights in current you're looking at the contem.
you're trying to classify you look at what words it has.
and then you look at what those weights are.
and you produce an answer as to what the probability.
of that document being classified with that label is.
and then you essentially output your list of your guesses if you will.
or the probabilities of those labels.
I know it's pretty it's a four people want to get started in this. it's a pretty easy one to implement.
I guess if I had to recommend a book.
there's a there's a great book on a lot of these things.
called programming collective intelligence.
which actually explains the algorithms and shows code on how to do these.
at a pretty simple level or she can go and take that from there.
my own action all also covers a lot of these things in detail to great.
well grant if our listeners would like to follow you and your thoughts how can they do that?
sure let's see I tend to blog at my company's website.
so lucid works Commons is my company and tend to blog there from time to time.
also my personal blog is grant Ingersoll comm.
and then on Twitter I am G s ing ers G singers if you will.
those are probably I guess the main three ways.
and speaking from time to time in various places.
and and I think as you mentioned at the top of the show.
I do have a book coming up called Timmy text.
which is essentially geared towards being an engineer's introduction to natural language processing.
search and machine learning using open source tools.
so what me and my fellow authors do in there is take take these common things.
like classification clustering search etc.
explain the basic principles behind them.
and then show examples of how to solve those problems.
you've been commonly used open source tools like solar and Lucie in.
like my house like open and LPD etc.
when will that book be out?
so we're in the final stages of editing and layout right now.
I don't know the exact date but I'm guessing they're probably towards the beginning of early January.
but maybe in December as well I'm not entirely certain as to what happens the process at the moment.
after the after layouts done I don't know how long it takes to.
if listeners would like to learn more about them to help project or maybe get involved.
what's the best way for them to do that?
my hot dog patchy org is the main URL for my hat on.
there there will be a number of links to our wiki page which.
has tools on how to contribute.
also has a lot of references to books and articles on how to end machine learning.
there's also so the mailing lists that which are described on the the main webpage as well.
it's a great place to just simply come ask questions about machine learning.
regardless of whether you use my house or not.
the people and practitioners there are typically pretty good.
about helping guide people to appropriate resources.
whether that's within our community or is better served somewhere else.
and if listeners would like to find out about lucid imagination what's the best way to do that?
yeah so actually we just recently changed our name for lucid imagination to lucid works.
so lucid works calm is our new website.
although lucid imagination calm will redirect you there.
and on there you know we've got a variety of resources.
people can also reach out to me grant at loose it works calm.
I'm gonna be happy to try to direct them in the right way to grant.
thank you very much for speaking to software engineering radio.
thank you I'm glad to be here.
thanks for listening to su radio.
an educational program brought to you by I Triple E software magazine.
for more information about the podcast including other episodes visit our website at se - radio net.
to support us you can advertise su radio by clicking the Digg reddit delicious or slash buttons.
on the site well by talking about this on Facebook Twitter or your own blog.
if you have feedback specific to an episode please use the commenting feature on the site.
so that other listeners can respond to your comments as well.
this and all of the episodes of se radio is licensed under the creative commons 2.5 license.
please see the website for details.
thanks again for your support.
[Music]
[Applause]